<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>For the vineyard of the Lord of hosts to be read in their meetings : the breathings of a prisoner for the testimony of Jesus, who in the deep hath seen the afflictions of his people, and cannot hide his praise who support them, nor-with-hold his complaint because of the hardness of mens hearts, but cryes unto the Lord God of righteous judgment, for the deliverance of his own people : with a few words of exhortation and advice, given forth as a testimony of my dearest love to the whole seed of God, because I cannot otherwise communicate it in this time of my restraint, I have been the more large, that I may be refreshed with you, and you with me, in the overflowing fountain of our life / by John Whitehead.</title>
            <author>Whitehead, John, 1630-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1977</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21528</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12297110</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12297110</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59061</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65900)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59061)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 930:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>For the vineyard of the Lord of hosts to be read in their meetings : the breathings of a prisoner for the testimony of Jesus, who in the deep hath seen the afflictions of his people, and cannot hide his praise who support them, nor-with-hold his complaint because of the hardness of mens hearts, but cryes unto the Lord God of righteous judgment, for the deliverance of his own people : with a few words of exhortation and advice, given forth as a testimony of my dearest love to the whole seed of God, because I cannot otherwise communicate it in this time of my restraint, I have been the more large, that I may be refreshed with you, and you with me, in the overflowing fountain of our life / by John Whitehead.</title>
                  <author>Whitehead, John, 1630-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Signed: John Whitehead.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59061:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59061:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FOR THE VINEYARD OF THE Lord of Hoſts, To be Read in Their MEETINGS.</p>
            <p>The BREATHINGS of a PRISONER for the TESTIMO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NY of JESUS, who in the Deep hath ſeen the <hi>Afflictions</hi> of his People, and cannot hide his Praiſe who ſupports them, nor-with-hold his Complaint becauſe of the hardneſs of mens hearts, but cryes unto the Lord God of Righteous Judgment, for the Deliverance of his own PEOPLE.</p>
            <p>With a few Words of <hi>Exhortation</hi> and <hi>Advice,</hi> given forth as a Teſtimony of my deareſt Love to the whole Seed of God; becauſe I cannot otherwiſe communicate it in this time of my Reſtraint, I have been the more large, that I may be refreſhed with you, and you with me, in the overflowing Fountain of our Life.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN WHITEHEAD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:59061:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59061:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>For the <hi>VINEYARD</hi> of the <hi>Lord of Hoſts,</hi> to be Read in their Meetings.</head>
            <p>O Vineyard of the Moſt High, wherein I have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured according to the ability which God hath given me ſince the appearing of the Bright and Morning-Star which hath enlightned the World, in whoſe Joy I am now at reſt, and my Peace is as a River, becauſe I hid not my Talent in the Earth, nor have ſtood idle in the Market-place, but have improved what was given me for my Maſter's uſe; and for the increaſe and watering of thee his Vineyard, which I cannot in any wiſe forget now when trouble is near, and all the Beaſts of the Field do compaſs thee about, and with their whole Power do ſeek to break down thy Hedge, crop off thy Leaves, devour thy Fruit, tread under thy tender Plants, cut off thy flouriſhing Branches, and make thee as a Wilderneſs: For in the everlaſting Love of one God I think upon thee, remembring the kindneſs of thy youth, and the love of thine Eſpouſals, wherein thou wert betrothed to the Lord with Judgment and Mercy, in the day that thou ſate ſolitary in the Wilderneſs, and had none to help: my heart is broken within me, and doth with thy breathing Babes and tender Mourners (whoſe Cry hath reached unto Heaven) ſend forth theſe <hi>Breathings,</hi> that in the Spirit of Supplication we may have fellowſhip together, whilſt my ſoul ſaith unto God, Surely thou haſt no caſt off the Beloved of thy Soul, nor ſold the Heritage (to be trodden down) for a thing of nought, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther given the Plants of thine own right-hand for a ſpoil to their Enemies: Shall they then prevail, which come gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their teeth to devour us? and wilt thou let thy Name be blaſphemed, wherein thou haſt gathered us, in which we do truſt? for thy Preſence is yet amongſt us, and thou with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeſt not the Riches of thy Mercy from us, but openeſt thy Treaſure to us; and of thy Fulneſs we have received ſtrength, elſe we could not have eſcaped in the hour of Temptation, nor
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59061:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtood upright in the time of our deep Tryals, but when thou ſaweſt us weak, thou turned not away thy Face from us, but ever haſt ſtretched out thy right-hand to uphold us, and haſt holpen us with a little help; when we call upon thee, thou boweſt down thine ear to hear, and giveſt us alſo to underſtand the words of thy mouth. But why doſt thou not ſhew thy ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, for they underſtand not thy way? For, though thou haſt given thy Light into the World, they love Darkneſs rather, and that blinds their eyes, that they know not thee, nor us whom thou haſt ſent, and therefore do perſecute and ſeek to root up, not believing that we are thy pleaſant Plants; although thou haſt created us anew in thine own Image, and ſhewed thy Light, Life, Love, Vertue, Power, Patience and good-will towards men, through us, yet do they not conſider, but think they do thee good ſervice, when they kill us all the day long: And when we do ſpeak to them in thy Name, and would turn them from their Envie, Anger, Pride, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Murders, Thefts, Lies, Adulteries, Fornications, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, Injuſtice, and the evil of their Inventions, unto the Light wherein thy Fulneſs dwells, that therein they might walk with thee in newneſs of life; They reject our Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſay we would delude them; and when we do declare thy Righteouſneſs, and ſhew thy Judgments at hand, becauſe Tranſgreſſions are multiplied, and Iniquity drunk up as water; their hearts they harden againſt us, and mock at fear, neither do they prepare to turn unto thee, but for our love in warning them, give us the water a Affliction to drink; and when we call them that are yet wandring with a heart panting for living water (but being gone aſtray from thy wayes, do drink of the Whores Cup, or, at beſt, that Water which men have fouled with their feet) and ſay, Turn ye again to the Lord, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file not your ſelves with the Inventions of men, neither touch any unclean thing, but come forth and <hi>be ye ſeparate,</hi> and our God will be a Father unto you, and you ſhall be his Children: Then they reproach us a <hi>factious, ſowers of Sedition:</hi> but if any do lay it to heart, and believe our Teſtimony and return, they meet them firſt with flatteries, then with threats and cruelties, which they ſpread, as the ſnares on <hi>Mizpah,</hi> for their feet, like
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59061:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the chief Prieſts Phariſees, and Lawyers of old, who would neither enter into the Kingdom themſelves, nor ſuffer thoſe that were entring to go on: And when we are gathered in thy Name, and do ſilently wait to feel thy Power, that in it we may edifie one another, and drink at the Fountain of Life, which thou haſt opened unto us, without reverance to thy Name, they come upon us with open violence to devour thy Lambs, meerly for drinking at the Fountain; yea, their ſtroke upon us is very cruel, becauſe we love thy Precepts, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not derogate from the glory of thy Verity, who haſt made out <hi>Yea, Yea,</hi> and our <hi>Nay, Nay;</hi> and ſaid unto us by thy Son ſince the Law, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and though we have given our cheeks to the ſmiter, our bodies to priſon, and expoſed our goods to the Spoiler, and patiently born many other grievous ſufferings for the Truths ſake, whereof thou haſt made us Witneſſes; yet will they not believe thoſe things which thou haſt ſpoken by us, and what have we more to ſeal the Teſtimony with which thou haſt given us? unleſs thou wilt ſuffer the Whore to drink more of the blood of thy Saints before thou bring thy long and often threatned Iudgments upon her, who yet fears them not, but ſaith, <hi>I ſit a Queen, and am no Widow, neither ſhall I ſee any ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row:</hi> And by what means wilt thou plead with <hi>Babylon</hi> that ſaith ſhe is the <hi>Lady</hi> of Kingdoms, or who ſhall perſwade men to fly out from her, that they periſh not in her plagues, for they are mad upon her <hi>Idols,</hi> and do mock thy Meſſengers, and do ſhamefully intreat and ſtone thoſe whom thou haſt ſent to forewarn them, that they may eſcape the wrath to come; Yet with thee is mercy and forgiveneſs, and I know thou wouldeſt not their deſtruction, but rather that they may turn and live: Therefore hear my Complaint, and bow thine ear to my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, for I groan within my ſelf and my ſpirit breathes that thou mayeſt ariſe in thy Mighty Power, and ſpeak by thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgments, that men may fear before thee, and the <hi>Nations</hi> be perſwaded to come to thy Light, and Kings to the brightneſs of thy riſing. Let thy right hand rent the vaile from off all hearts, that thy <hi>Salvation</hi> may be ſhewed openly, and <hi>Satan</hi> trodden under foot, for who elſe is ſufficient for theſe things. But in the day of <hi>Indignation,</hi> O Lord, Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59061:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>thine <hi>Heritage,</hi> and let not thy <hi>Vineyard</hi> be rooted up, but ſpare thy People, and cauſe thy tender Plants to grow: Chain the Dragon, and let the Earth drink up the floods that would hinder thy Spouſe from returning out of the Wilderneſs, where her place hath been in the long dark night of Apoſtacy: but ſince the breaking up of the day, thou haſt ſaid unto her that ſate ſolitary, I am the Husband of thy youth, therefore walk with me, and I will not leave thee nor forſake thee, but lead thee unto the Mountain of my Houſe, and my Banner over thee ſhall be Love, and herewith thou haſt allured her, and ſhe followeth hard after thee: But now, O Lord, our Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, we are compaſſed about with Adverſaries, and grievous Wolves are gathered to prey upon thy Lambs, Therefore abide thou with us, and break their teeth, O God, that thy Flock may not be meat for them; for our expectation is from thee alone, and we have not made fleſh our Arm, becauſe our hope is in thee; neither tribulations nor afflictions can ſeparate us from thee, for we have appealed unto thy Righteouſneſs, who ſearcheſt the hearts and tryeſt the reins of all men, that thou mayeſt give Judgement between us and them that do afflict us; and if thou haſt not ſent us and commanded us to ſpeak, or if in heart we be not innocent towards men, and no way guilty of doing or intending thoſe evils wherewith they charge us, Then let out hearts fail, and confuſion cover us before them in the day of our Tryal; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd if thou haſt ſent us and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to ſpeak, and by thy own Power begotten us into an innocent life, Then open thou our lips, and let the words of thy mouth break through us, and ſtick in the hearts of our Enemies, that they may be pricked like the Perſecutors of old, and not have ability to reſiſt the Spirit and Wiſdom by which thou leadeſt us: for though we our ſelves know that we are of thee, yet do we patiently wait till thou decide the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, and in the ſight of all men ſhew who are thy People; yet can I not ceaſe to breath, that thou mayeſt ſhorten theſe dayes of trouble for thy Elect ſake, in whom thy ſoul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth, that no more may be laid upon thy little ones than they can bear, leſt they faint, and their Adverſaries triumph and ſay, <hi>Where is now the God in whom they truſted?</hi> O let them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59061:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>know that thou art near, and doſt hear the cry of the Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and upon the Glory of thy Name let there be a defence, and ſo keep us in it, to the end that it may never be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured.</p>
            <p>Now having refreſhed my full heart, in ſpreading our Cauſe before the Lord, O ye his People bear with me a little, and let your ears be enclined to hear a few things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns your peace: for, becauſe I love you, I cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from you, that it is ſignified unto me, That whilſt you are beſet with Adverſaries on every ſide, the Enemy will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtir himſelf-with all ſubtilty and violence to make a breach amongſt you, and alſo will tempt to every thing whereby he may weaken you, and let your Adverſaries in upon you; but he ſhall not be able to effect his purpoſe, whilſt you all, in that Faith which worketh by Love, Meekneſs and Gentleneſs, do hold the <hi>one Head,</hi> which is Chriſt the Light, and neither the Planters nor the Waterers: for Him we preached, and in Him we have believed who is the Author of Eternal Salvation from Sin, and perfecter of Man's Redemption up to God, and you are Witneſſes that we have not preached up our ſelves, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther laboured to ſet up him that planteth, nor him that watereth, as any thing in compariſon of the precious Truth of God, for which we now ſuffer, but in plainneſs and ſincerity, not with <hi>wiſdom of words,</hi> but <hi>in the demonſtration of the Spirit</hi> we have manifeſted the Life and Power of God, that ye may know, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and be guided by it in your ſelves, and ſo inherit Reſt and Peace with God, and not alwayes ſtand afar off, in the expectation of ſomewhat to come, which is an unſetled ſtate, wherein they that ſtand may eaſily be deceived with ſwelling words, or good pretences, wherewith the ſtrange Woman (whoſe wayes are movable) decketh her ſelf, leſt thoſe whom ſhe ſeeks to catch in her ſnare ſhould ponder the path of Life, and ſee that her wayes do lead to the Chambers of death, and that her ſteps take hold on Hell.</p>
            <p>But dearly belove Friends and Brethren, ſeeing we know that the Son of God is come by an, innard feeling of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in ſpirit, that hath given us an underſtanding that is true, and we look not for another, but are rooted and grounded
<pb facs="tcp:59061:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>in him, Let us hold faſt our confidence, and faithfully fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, and patiently endure the Croſs, that we may ever be his Diſciples, who is a quickning Spirit and doth dwell in us; then ſhall we no more wander amongſt bryars and thorns, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> amongſt the Lillies of the Valley, and drink of the Water of Life.</p>
            <p>But Friends, becauſe all of you that are convinced are not yet come into the ſavoury Life, to diſcern of things that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, you muſt ſake heed of preſuming to judge of things that are, beyond your meaſure, for your principle, ſtrength and ſafety is to be ſtill, and wait in he Light of the Spirit <hi>within,</hi> that both your Faith and Wiſdom from above may be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and that will open you more and more to receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, but will never let you ſlight nor reject the Spirit's Teſtimony in the Elders and Brethren, whom God did uſe as Inſtruments to turn yow unto him, which ſtill in the ſame. Love do watch over your Souls; Neither ſhall you deſpiſe Propheſying, not quench the Spirit that ſpeaks in the mouth of Babes who are of ſtammeting lips; but as Friends of the Bridegroom, rejoyce to hear his Voice in any inſtrument, by whom, or to whom never he ſpeaks<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But take diligent heed leſt you ſet tip any Inſtrument above its place, or give unto it any part of the Glory that is due unto him that uſeth it, leſt thereby ye kindle his Wrath, and cauſe jealouſie to burn like a Fire: for if his Glory he given to, and received by the moſt precious Inſtrument in his hand, be will caſt it away from him, and ſuffer it to be trodden under foot as the mire of the ſtreets. Therefore be tender of one anothers preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and let all your affections be guided with Juſtice, Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Moderation, ſo ſhall you never puff up any above, not caſt down any below the in meaſure, which doth much tend to preſerve the Body in the unity of the Spirit and bouds of Peace.</p>
            <p>And you that are his Children in ſimplicity, wait that ye alſo in underſtanding may be Men, and take heed of being ſo affected with ſimplicity, as to deſpiſe or hate knowledge, like thoſe to whom Wiſdom cryed, and Underſtanding ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered her voice, and they would not hear; who ſtood con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59061:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>in ignorance, till calamity came upon them, like an armed man, but alwayes bow down your ears to the Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Life, and do the Will of God, that ye may underſtand Doctrine and be of a ſound Judgment to try Spirits and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, whether they be of God or no: but in ſo doing, be ſure to keep your own habitations in a meaſure of light, and ſee that neither prejudice nor immoderate affections bear ſway in you, ſo will you ſee what ſtands in Unity with the firſt Principle, by which you were turned towards God, and is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in his Light, and tends to ſtabliſh you in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that you may ſafely imbrace; but whatſoever doth jar with the firſt Principle, and would diſ-ſettle and remove you from the <hi>Light within</hi> (wherein that which may be known of God is made manifeſt) either by drawing into uncouth and ſingular outward Obſervations, or by promiſing Liberty, or a greater Glory than that which the Light of the Spirit within hath given us to behold with open face, as in a Glaſs, and is tranſlating you thereinto; I ſay, that which by theſe things would work diſcontent in your preſent meaſures, and let you looſe from waiting in God's Fear, into the comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of things above your meaſures, is dangerous, and to be eſchewed: And if any do hold forth ſuch things, they, as well as ſuch which would draw you back into the Rudiments of the World, do ſpeak of themſelves, and ſeek their own glory; but he whom God hath ſent, ſpeaketh the words of God, and ſeeketh his Glory that ſent him.</p>
            <p>And if Contention, Strife, Wars, or Commotions do ariſe in the Earth, betwixt Man and Man, or People and People where you inhabit, dwell you in that Power which hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed you out of the Earth from amongſt Men, and that will keep you ſenſible that you are not your own, but bought with a price, <hi>that you may be unto God a peculiar People;</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſhall not defile your ſelves with their Contentions, nor ſtrive, nor ſide with Parties, which fly to that Sword for refuge by which they may periſh: but we having received and truſted in the Sword of the Spirit, by which we can never periſh, let us ſit down in that which keeps holy and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and ſeparate from ſinners; ſo ſhall his wonderful Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59061:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>who is Prince of Peace, be with us, wherein we may be Peace-makers, and obtain the bleſſing to be called <hi>the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you that are as yet not much exerciſed with Sufferings, but are at peace in your dwellings, none making you afraid, Take heed leſt at any time you be ſecure; for then may the Enemy intice you from a ſence of God's mercy to look out at Creatures, and to ſet your heart on Earthly things, and then if a tryal come ſuddenly and unexpected, it will be the heavier upon you; and if through want of preparation ye fall under in it, then it will be hard for you to be raiſed up again to ſtand faithful unto the End, whereon your ſafety and the poſſdeſſion of the Crown of Life depends: and if you be not conſtant and faithful in theſe laſt tryals, you loſe your reward, for all that ye have gone through: for, if any do put his hand to the plough, and look back, my ſoul hath no pleaſure in him, ſaith the Lord. Therefore, as I would that you ſhould not be diſmaid, nor fear the Threatnings, Excommunications, Fines and Impriſonments, or any other thing which you may ſuffer by the wicked hands of mortal men; So would I that you may both inwardly and outwardly be prepared to ſuffer what man can do unto you: And whilſt ye behold the Lord reſtraining their wrath from breaking out againſt you, bear a part with your Brethren that are ſuffering under it, and God ſhall reckon it to you in the day of your need.</p>
            <p>Finally, dear Friends and Brethren, be of one mind, and live in peace, and in the Name of the Lord keep your Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, that Love and Life may abound amongſt you, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in faithfully inſtruct, admoniſh, and (if need be) reprove one another; but let the Spirit judge all things, and with an open tender heart receive Inſtruction and Reproof one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, pondring it in deep ſilence, and not meaſuring it in the reaſoning part, for that will grow high and work prejudice againſt the Admoniſher and Reprover, if you ſee not a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent cauſe or need of ſuch a thing, and thereby you may both hurt your ſelves, and diſcourage thoſe that in ſincerity ſought your good, whereby they may be cauſed in ſilence to lament when they ſee you in the like danger, and ſay, <hi>We called, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59061:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>they would not hear:</hi> therefore meaſure and bear all things in the meek low ſpirit. And you that are ſtrong and ſpiritually minded, being come over all theſe things, labour to reſtore and raiſe up them that fall, and comfort the feeble-minded, and ſay to them that ſtand afar off, Draw near and walk with us in the Light, and the Lord will alſo give you reſt; and wait on your Miniſtry, that ye may preſerve that which is gathered in the ſavoury Life, to ſhine as Lights before men; For there is a Seed ſown in this Nation and elſewhere, which begins to bud forth in thouſands, who having not ſeen, yet love; which gives me ſufficient ground to believe that when the Winter is paſt, and the latter Rain comes upon the Earth, the ſhall be a plentiful Harveſt, wherein every one that hath been faithful in a little, ſhall reap much, and give thanks unto God which hath bleſſed the Seed ſown, who will ſend forth ſuch, as in the furnace of Affliction he hath fitted for his uſe, faithfully to labour, that every eye may be opened to ſee the common Salvation (that God hath prepared for all People) is the Light that doth enlighten the Gentiles, and the Glory of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written in <hi>Lincoln-Caſtle</hi>
                  <date>the 24th day of the ſixth Month, 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>John Whitehead.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
